Furnas, Heather Collection of Sidney Hillman Foundation Awards Research Materials 6364
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Heather Furnas Collection of Sidney Hillman Foundation Awards Research Materials
1957-1967
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Furnas, Heather
Sidney Hillman Foundation
6364
0.5 cubic feet
0.5 linear ft.
Articles, reprints, pamphlets, correspondence.
8300043
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, November 20, 2013
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, January 31, 2014
Biographical / Historical
The Sidney Hillman Foundation was named for the labor leader, Sidney Hillman (1887-1946), who was the first president of the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America (ACWA). Immediately after his death, his union wished to honor him with a memorial that would carry on his commitments to the lives of working people. On November 17, 1946, the General Executive Board of the ACWA voted to establish the Sidney Hillman Foundation. ACWA contributed the first $100,000 and then raised one million dollars from other organizations. In 1947, the Board of Directors issued the first grants for scholarships, research and lectures on college campuses, and for medical research at the Sidney Hillman Health Centers.
In 1950, the Foundation launched the Hillman Prize in order to promote socially-responsible journalism. Starting with awards in Book, Magazine, Newspaper, and Broadcast, the prize is now also offered in the categories of Photojournalism, Web, and Opinion and Analysis. One important note is that the Hillman Foundation changed its dating system for prizes in 1999/ 2000. The Foundation decided to name the prize for the year it was given rather than the year the work was produced, changing the pattern of the previous fifty years. This new system continues to the present. This means that in effect there are no prizes for the year 1999, but a year was not skipped in the granting of awards.
Scope and Contents
The Hillman Prize has been granted annually by the Sidney Hillman Foundation since 1950 in categories that included Book, Newspaper, and Magazine. The Foundation did not keep complete citations for the articles, nor retain copies of the award-winning submissions. Heather Furnas was contracted by the Hillman Foundation in order to locate the citations for the award-winning newspaper and magazine articles and to obtain copies when possible. Included in the collection is an excel document with tabs for each of the prize categories. The researcher included the complete citation, links if available and indicated if digital copies were obtained. In separate files, there are .pdf files of what the researcher determined to be the winning articles, organized by type of publication and year.
At a later date, the researcher was asked to locate transcripts of the lectures that were a part of the Hillman Lectureship Program. If a transcript was located, a copy was placed in the Lectures folder. The researcher also tried to obtain newspaper articles regarding these lectures, especially if they gave summaries. The best place to obtain a complete list of the lecturers is in the "Twenty-Year Report," found Collection #5619/040 Box 2, Folder 8 and copied into this collection. There is also a complete listing of the Reprint Series.
Some newspaper citations were particularly difficult to track down, and are therefore based on the researcher's best determination. Some awards were granted without titles of particular articles, but rather the body of work of the journalist and themes that were addressed. For example, Murray Kempton was granted the first newspaper award in 1950 for articles on "labor in the south." The digital files obtained on Murray Kempton come from the clippings file in Box 1 Folder 3 (1950) in the Murray Kempton Papers at Columbia's Rare Book and Manuscript Library. They are unsorted, and the researcher did not make a determination on which articles won the prize.
Also included in the collection are photocopies from Merrill G. Burlingame Special Collections at Montana State University, which hold the papers for Harry L. and Gretchen Billings, newspaper award winners in 1958 for their "editorials on civil liberties and public welfare system" in the People's Voice. These copies come from collection #2095, Box 2, Folder 28-32, which are all labeled "Hillman Award Correspondence"; "Hillman Award Clippings" come from Box 2, Folder 33. These documents might reveal to researchers the process of nomination and selection for the prizes in general, and these award winners in particular, but do not contain the newspaper articles.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 6098: Sidney Hillman Foundation Prize for Tom Darcy Newsday Cartoons 6098 MB: Sidney Hillman Foundation Banners. Memorabilia. 6200/004: UNITE HERE. Sidney Hillman Foundation Awards.
Sidney Hillman Foundation
8300043
- Harry Billings Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Sidney Hillman Foundation 20 Year Report (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Hillman Award Correspondence from Merrill G. Burlingame Special Collections, Harry Billings Collection, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Scope and Contents
    Collection no.2095: Box 2: ff 28
  - Hillman Award Correspondence from Merrill G. Burlingame Special Collections, Harry Billings Collection, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Collection no.2095: Box 2: ff 29
  - Hillman Award Correspondence from Merrill G. Burlingame Special Collections, Harry Billings Collection, 1957-1959 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Collection no.2095: Box 2: ff 30
  - Hillman Award Correspondence from Merrill G. Burlingame Special Collections, Harry Billings Collection, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Collection no.2095: Box 2: ff 31
  - Hillman Award Correspondence from Merrill G. Burlingame Special Collections, Harry Billings Collection, 1959-1967 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Collection no.2095: Box 2: ff 32
  - Hillman Award Clippings from Merrill G. Burlingame Special Collections, Harry Billings Collection, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Collection no.2095: Box 2: ff 33
- Lectures: directory of PDFs (Box 2)
  - Hillman Lecture List (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Sub-Series Transcripts
    - Anderson at Roosevelt--transcript (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Bunche, Howard, 1964 The world the United Nations seeks - Lecture Howard University, Washington, D.C. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Humphrey, Alliance for Progress, U. of Minnesota (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Lester, Revolution in Industrial Employment (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Rand 1951University of Toronto (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Smith, Roosevelt, transcript (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Sub-Series Clippings regarding lectures
    - Announcement of lectures series 1954.pdf (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Boas to Deliver Hillman Lectures.pdf (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Eleanor Roosevelt, Minnesota1957-03-06.pdf (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Sub-Series City College
      - City College 1958 UN Experts.pdf (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - City College 1958.pdf (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Sub-Series Howard University
      - 1961 John Hope Frankin.pdf (Box 2, Folder 13)
      - Howard University 1954-1955.pdf (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - James MacGregor Burns.pdf (Box 2, Folder 15)
      - John Hope Frankin Talks on Civil Rights.pdf (Box 2, Folder 16)
      - Keyerling, Howard University Series 54-55.pdf (Box 2, Folder 17)
      - Tugwell December 1959.pdf (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Sub-Series New School
      - (1955) Howe, The Challenge to Liberty ,New School.pdf (Box 2, Folder 19)
      - New School.pdf (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Sub-Series Roosevelt University
      - 1956 Chicago.pdf (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Sub-Series University of Rochester
      - Thurgood Marshall.pdf (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Magazine Articles: directory of PDFs (Box 3)
  - Means, Best Medicine for the Patient, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    1950 related
  - Means, Government in Medicine, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Means, Doctor's Lobby, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Means, England's Public Medicine, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Morse, Who's Trying To Ruin Our Schools, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Wechberg, Seventeenth of June, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Knight, What Price Security, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - The Progressive Special Issue on McCarthy, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Engler, Oil and Politics Part I, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Engler, Oil and Politics, Parts II-VI, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Fischer, Harm Good People Do, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Santillana, Galileo and J. Robert Oppenheimer, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Sardos, Myth of the Powerful Worker, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Ernst & Drake, Poor, Proud and Primitive, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Smith, Ordeal of the Southern Woman, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Parton, Sometimes Life Just Happens, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Hano, Burned Out Americans, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Draper, Dominican Crisis, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Harris, Medicare Part I, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Harris, Medicare Part II, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Harris, Medicare Part III, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Harris, Medicare Part IV, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Remsberg, America's Hungry Families, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Lang, Casualties of War, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Pyle, CONUS Part I, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Pyle, CONUS Part II, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Donner and Cerutti, Grand Jury Network, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Brodeur, Casualties of the Workplace Part I, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Brodeur, Casualties of the Workplace Part II, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Brodeur, Casualties of the Workplace Part III, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Brodeur, Casualties of the Workplace Part IV, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Brodeur, Casualties of the Workplace Part V, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Sheehan, A Welfare Mother, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Williams, The Mushroom Pickers, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Marshall, Anatomy of Healthcare Costs, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Kidder, Soldiers of Misfortune, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Brown, Love Canal and the Poisoning of America, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Angolite, Louisiana Death Watch, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Drew, Politics and Money Part I, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Drew, Politics and Money Part II, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Sagan, Nuclear War, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Salisbury, Strange Correspondence, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Sharkey, Tug of War, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Ford, The Button Part I, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Ford, The Button Part iI, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - O'Brien, God and Man in Nicaragua, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Adler, Every Parent's Nightmare, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Weschler, Grand Experiment, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Clancy, Burnout in LA, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Clancy, Healing the Delta, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Udesky, Punishing the Poor, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Schlefer, What Price Economic Growth, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Bates, et al, Poverty, Inc., 1993 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Bernstein, Why America Needs Unions But Not The Kind It Has Now, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Schlosser, In the Strawberry Fields, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Bowden, While You Were Sleeping, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Finnegan, The Unwanted, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Barlett and Steele, Corporate Welfare Empire of the Pigs, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Barlett and Steele, Corporate Welfare Fantasy Islands, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Barlett and Steele, Corporate Welfare Paying the Price for Polluters, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Barlett and Steele, Corporate Welfare, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Ehrenreich, Nickel and Dimed, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - Roberts et al, Workers in Bondage, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Boo, After Welfare, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - Bowe, Nobodies, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - Evans et al, Big Pharma's Shameful Secret, 2006 (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Noah, Great Divergence, 2011 (Box 3, Folder 67)
- Newspaper Articles: directory of PDFs (Box 4)
  - Kempton, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Jenkins, Again, the Klan Old Sheets, New Victims, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Bagdikian, What Price Security, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Spiegel, Segregation in Des Moines, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Arkansas Gazette, Bombs and Justice, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Atlanta Constitution, No Law Condones Rule by Violence, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Billings, People's Voice, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - McGill editorials, Atlanta Constitution, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Harkey clippings, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Harkey, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Emmerich, McComb Enterprise-Journal, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - James, Crisis in the Courts, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Batten and Walls, The People Left Behind, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Eaton, Chicago Daily News, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Eaton, from Pulitzer Prize, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Eaton, picked up by Washington Post, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Friendly, Victim of the Great American Red Hunt, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Barlett & Steele, Oil The Created Crisis, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - 54 Who Died, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Seigenthaler, The Tennessean, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Swofford, Greensboro Daily News, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Flannery & Ingersoll, Working Wounded, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Miami Herald, Police Brutality, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Atlanta Constitution, Black and Poor in Atlanta, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Ciolli, Island Trees Case, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Owens, Collection Nightmare December 18-19, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Owens, Disability Nightmare March 20-22, 1983 plus followups (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Clarion-Ledger,Freedom Summer a Generation Later, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Drug testing on the job, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Anchorage Daily News, A People In Peril, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - William H. and Margaret Wolf Freivogel, Shift on Civil Rights, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Detroit Free Press ,Workers at Risk, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Stancill, Slaves to the Sale, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Welsome, Plutonium Experiment, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Morris, Houston Chronicle, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Kelley, Whither the Cities, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Giordano and Lubrano, Philadelphia Inquirer, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - DeParle, Learning Poverty Firsthand, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - DeParle, Welfare to Work- A Sequel, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Mitchell, The Preacher and the Klansman, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Schultz, Wall Street Journal, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Olinger, Seller Beware, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Schultz & Francis, Valued Employees, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Callimachi, Children of the Storm, 2007 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Reinemer, A Southern City Debates Nonsegregation (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Sub-Series Boston Globe, School Desegregation, 1974
    - Cohen and Worsham, Boston Globe's school balance plan, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 46)
      April 1, 1974.
    - Cohen, Suburban cooperation to be topic in round 3 of imbalance hearing, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 47)
      April 7, 1974.
    - Cohen, Busing not main cause of flight to suburbs, study shows, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 48)
      April 11, 1974.
    - Cohen, In Pasadens: 2 schools and 2 schools of thought, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 49)
      April 21, 1974.
    - Cohen, School desegregation... a tale of five cities, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 50)
      April 25, 1974.
    - Cohen, Gillette plans high school 'partnership', 1974 (Box 4, Folder 51)
      August 24, 1974.
    - Cohen, Schools and colleges in state prepare for dramatic changes, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 52)
      January 6, 1974.
    - Cohen, Suburban cooperation to be topic in round 3 of imbalance hearing, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 53)
      display_pdf-17: April 7, 1974.
    - Cohen, Wishing, appeal probably won't make racial balance plan go away, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 54)
      February 17, 1974.
    - Cohen, White outlines stand on school balancing, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 55)
      February 2, 1974.
    - Cohen, Miss Sullivan urges year's delay in balancing schools, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 56)
      February 20, 1974.
    - Cohen, Imbalance: Boston's 3-front battle, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 57)
      February 24, 1974.
    - Cohen, Kerrigan vows 'revelations' on desegregation, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 58)
      January 8, 1974.
    - Cohen, Drift towards desegregation, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 59)
      January 14, 1974.
    - Cohen, Changes in Boston plan on racial imbalance due today, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 60)
      January 15, 1974.
    - Cohen, What's metropolitan education? A city to suburbs link, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 61)
      January 16, 1974.
    - Cohen, Boston hopes to free Federal funds frozen after '73 segregation ruling, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 62)
      July 3, 1974.
    - Cohen, Home and school assn. wants court OK to help make busing 'practical', 1974 (Box 4, Folder 63)
      July 4, 1974.
    - Cohen, School balancing: how much this fall?, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 64)
      July 14, 1974.
    - Cohen, Parents want classes out of English HS, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 65)
      July 16, 1974.
    - Cohen, Boston warns Garrity of school delay, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 66)
      July 17, 1974.
    - Cohen, New state panel to strive for quality education, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 67)
      July 21, 1974.
    - Cohen, The birth, death and legacy of the Massachusetts Racial Imbalance Law, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 68)
      July 28, 1974.
    - Cohen, Court action expected if Sargent balance plan passes, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 69)
      June 2, 1974.
    - Cohen, Special Ed law upsets some parents, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 70)
      June 6, 1974.
    - Cohen, King tells how he'd OK Sargent's school plan, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 71)
      June 7, 1974.
    - Cohen, Black history test for teachers, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 72)
      June 9, 1974.
    - Cohen, Court enforcement of balance plan to be asked, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 73)
      June 16, 1974.
    - Cohen, Bracing for trauma of Hub racial balancing, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 74)
      June 30, 1974.
    - Cohen, Pros and cons of school busing, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 75)
      March 3, 1974.
    - Cohen, A novel idea: School based on Mass. av., 1974 (Box 4, Folder 76)
      March 17, 1974.
    - Cohen, Federal, state bills not much threat to Boston busing plan, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 77)
      March 28, 1974.
    - Cohen, Prince George's County, Md.: A case of crash desegregation, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 78)
      May 5, 1974.
    - Cohen, Sargent struggling to retain balance law's principle but ease its impact, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 79)
      May 5b, 1974.
    - Cohen, Hub, Springfield balancing plans are unaffected, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 80)
      May 11, 1974.
    - Cohen, Questions and answers on the impact of Gov. Sargent's substitute balance plan, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 81)
      May 22, 1974.
    - Cohen, Busing schedules take shape amid court fights, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 82)
      May 26, 1974.
    - Cohen, Start due on total desegregation plan, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 83)
      October 1, 1974.
    - Cohen, Leary rejects bid by teachers union to shut schools, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 84)
      October 9, 1974.
    - Cohen, Training to begin for school workers, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 85)
      September 2, 1974.
    - Cohen, Colleges asked: aid integration, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 86)
      September 4, 1974.
    - Cohen, Study criticizes HEW for going slow in initiating discrimination cases in North, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 87)
      September 6, 1974.
    - Cohen, Desegregation and the oft-missing ingredents of quality education, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 88)
      September 8, 1974.
    - Cohen, School Committee votes double sessions for Dorchester High, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 89)
      September 10, 1974.
    - Cohen, Supt. Leary spent a long opening school day on emotional roller coaster, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 90)
      September 13, 1974.
    - Cohen, 3 Boston information centers busy tracking down desegregation rumors, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 91)
      September 26, 1974.
    - Cohen, Judge sets Dec. 16 deadline for Phase 2 plan, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 92)
      September 28, 1974.